- Ladies and gentlemen,
thank you for coming to our panel on,
what's the name of this panel?
It is Policy in Motion: Developing AI Guidelines.
And my name is Lynn Dickinson.
I am the panel moderator.
I just get to sit up here with these esteemed gentlemen
and bask in the glow of their knowledge,
which is really cool because they know a lot.
So, I'm a full-time faculty member at Santa Monica College.
I am the author of a couple of books on AI.
I have spoken,
done keynotes and stuff all over the world on it actually.
And what else do I do?
Oh, there's a course called EDUC-50 at Santa Monica College
that any professor from any college or university can take.
It's called Teaching in the Age of AI.
And we've been teaching it for,
you know, you enroll as a student
and it's a three unit class
and we've been teaching it for about five semesters now,
and including the intersessions.
And we've got faculty, we've had law professors from Drexel
and faculty from USC and UCLA
and all the different community colleges.
So, that one's been interesting
because we do touch on policy in that one, too,
for individual, because every discipline, every subject,
every department is different in their AI policy needs.
So, we're gonna talk a bit more about that here.
And I want to introduce you to the panelists a little bit.
I'll just say a little bit about them
and then give them each a chance
to introduce themselves a little bit more fully.
To my immediate left, we have Rodrigo Gomez.
He's an English faculty member
at Miramar College in San Diego,
and he's a faculty specialist for emerging technology.
And boy is he good at it.
- Hi everybody, my name is Rodrigo,
and like Lynn said, I teach full-time English
at San Diego Miramar College.
I've also been working for the last two and a half years
or so since a lot of this mess started at the district
through the Office of Institutional Innovation
and Effectiveness, just doing a lot
of professional development across San Diego.
And, you know, I've gone and done some presentations,
keynotes, workshops, everything you can think of
at this point that relates to AI and AI policy.
So, thank you for having me.
- Yeah, thank you, Rodrigo.
And then we also have on Rodrigo's left, Craig Hayward,
the visiting executive
for the Strategic Research and Innovative Design
for the California Community Colleges Chancellor's Office.
Craig, say more.
- Okay, I'll say a little bit more.
Yeah, that's quite the title.
I've been at the California Community College
Chancellor's Office for the past two plus years.
And one of the charges that the Chancellor gave me
is to coordinate the Chancellor's Office engagement with AI.
And that's one of the core directions of the Vision 2030,
which is really kind of our strategic guiding document.
I'm sure everyone in the room has heard of it.
And so generative AI, the future of teaching and learning,
has just really taken off
over the past two and a half years.
So, it was very appropriate to include it at a high level
in the Vision 2030.
But there's a lot, it's just such a wide area
that AI touches on.
There's a lot of activity,
a lot of other players that are involved in that space.
So, hence the need for coordination and policy development,
which is something the field has been asking for.
So in my role there, I've hosted a series of webinars
on generative AI applications in higher education.
And we're gonna kick off a new series
on September 30th of this year.
And this time around,
they're gonna be followed by deep dives.
So we'll do the usual one-hour session,
Tuesdays 12:00 to 1:00,
and then on Friday we're gonna do an hour and a half
or two hours where we kind of get deep,
you know, go deeper into exploring how to implement
some of the cool technology that we highlight
in the main webinar.
Other related work,
also one of the leaders of the Digital Center,
the new innovative design and evaluation,
technology-centric, equity-centric partnership
between the Chancellor's Office and Foothill-De Anza.
So, that's really beginning to take off as well.
And then other projects like Nectar AI pilot,
do we have anyone in the room who has participated in,
is a Nectar AI pilot member, other than just Rodrigo?
Okay, well, oh, okay. Couple of us in here.
And then PlayLab. Any PlayLab cohort members?
Okay, there we go. This is the PlayLab room.
And I was in the first cohort of PlayLab as well.
That's a fantastic technology.
Really exciting.
And then of course, the Common Cloud,
which is kind of a 21st century data platform that,
thinking of as AI-ready.
So that's some of the things
that are in my portfolio at the Chancellor's Office.
And a little bit about me, I have been a member
of the California Community College system since 2001.
My background's largely research
and kind of innovative research
and developing some statewide tools,
things that are in the DataMart like that.
So, that's some of my background.
Let me hand it back to Lynn
to continue with the introductions.
- Perfect. Good job.
All right, so, our hero of the day
who just is rescuing us by joining the panel
at the last minute is Kevin Kelly,
the Interim Executive Director of Transformation and Equity
for California Community College's Digital Center
for Innovation.
And thank you for filling that seat.
Tell us more. Tell us more.
- How about now?
Okay. Hi everybody.
So as Lynn mentioned, I am Kevin Kelly.
I'm the Interim Executive Director of the Digital Center
that also Craig mentioned as part of his portfolio.
I've been in higher ed since I think before time began.
And so it's been a while.
I like the framing that Meredith said today,
these are just wisdom lines in my hair.
But in some of my roles,
I've been a consultant around the country
for colleges and universities on a variety of things.
But AI has popped up. You might have heard of it.
It's a topic people are talking about.
And I had the privilege to co-facilitate
a summit this summer with Educause
around adopting AI
and what are the challenges that the colleges
around the country and universities are facing.
So, hopefully I can bring some of the ideas
that were generated from that
and some of my other work to the table.
But in my role as the executive director
for the Digital Center, I'm committed to partnering
with the Chancellor's Office to create opportunities
so that the colleges don't have to work in silos, right?
One of the biggest things that we're hearing
is that people feel like they're reinventing wheels.
They want to talk to colleagues who are doing the same work.
Should we develop something like a policy or a guideline?
Which is better?
And how long will it last
if the technology keeps changing so quickly?
So, we'll get into that in our conversation today.
But I just wanted to put out there,
feel free to contact me if you're looking for ways
to collaborate around policy development
or at least reviewing the policies that you currently have.
- Thank you, Kevin. I appreciate that.
So, we're gonna explore some questions around policy,
which we have a list of them thanks to Craig.
So, let's start with what do students, faculty,
and administrators and classified professionals
need to know about AI?
Gentlemen. Somebody say something intelligent.
- I think it's been, well,
I think it's been suggested at this conference already
that it's not going anywhere and that it's here to stay.
And that we're gonna have to adjust,
come to terms with what the technology is
and support our students
by being very transparent about the things
that we put into our syllabus, including AI policies.
That at the bare minimum I think is a good way to start.
- I'll reiterate what the Chancellor said this morning
at the opening keynote session in the theater,
which is we need to have an understanding
that we're promoting a culture
of AI literacy across the system.
And I think this is where the policy conversation
is headed now.
And that means that there's a baseline of AI literacy.
So, what is AI literacy?
And we do have that handy acronym,
PEOPLE, to remind us of the fundamentals.
And that work on that acronym came from the AI Council,
which is a group of about 25 individuals
from all across the system in different roles.
A lot of faculty representation on that body.
And it's been extremely helpful.
So, that's the group that developed the HUMANS Principles,
but also PEOPLE which stands for,
you know, prompting with purpose.
That's the P. E is ethics first.
O is observe and verify.
This is my first public demonstration of this,
so we'll see if I can actually pull it off.
- So far so good.
- So far so good, right?
I just jinxed myself.
What's the second P, is,
oh yeah, we're kind of split on this one.
So, the Chancellor said processor not person,
AI council, you know, felt,
well, maybe we want to say personify wisely,
but that second P is really about understanding
that an AI is not a sentient individual, it's not a person.
And so kind of maintaining some emotional air gap
between yourself and that AI for your mental health.
And L, learn the basics.
So, we don't have to be computer scientists or AI experts,
Lord knows I'm not.
But if you understand the fundamentals of how a GPT,
you know, an LLM works, the training,
that can be very helpful to you as you become literate.
And then E, committing to evolve continuously.
Because obviously as we know, you know,
every week, every month there's kind of a new advance
and something new happening.
And so just because something worked one way last month
doesn't mean that's gonna be,
you know, you can set it and forget it.
So that's our PEOPLE,
kind of the six fundamentals we feel all students,
all faculty, all classified professionals,
all administrators should have that.
So, how do we achieve that is really the question.
How do we leverage policy to make AI literacy
something that's real for everyone?
- They've said so many great things.
But, so I'll pick up on some of the themes
that have been brought out.
A couple weeks ago I was at San Joaquin Delta College.
Any folks from Delta College here?
No? They had their convocation.
And I did a workshop for, I don't know,
maybe 150 faculty and staff around AI.
It was called AI 101.
And because I'm a fan of interaction,
so I passed the mic around and a lot of them said
what we heard before, AI's here to stay.
But there was a clear call to action
that we need to be aware of the equity challenges.
And I like how Don Daves-Rougeaux
brought it up this morning.
We need the healthy skeptics in the room
to help us do this responsibly.
But the charge from the faculty in the room at Delta College
was, we cannot amplify equity barriers or a digital divide.
And so being conscious of that, again,
with equity being in the name for the Digital Center,
we'll be looking at how do we create opportunities
for everybody to participate
and how do we create room for everyone
to join the discussion.
As someone who's taught for 25 years, in my own syllabus,
which I loved the skit today that was like
♪ It's in the syllabus ♪
- That was the best.
- But it says specifically,
because my class has been called
How to Learn with your Mobile Device.
So, I'm teaching students how to learn
and how to use technology for learning purposes.
And I say we're gonna talk about using AI
as a learning tool, but we're also gonna talk about
the difference between using it and abusing it, right?
And so I mentioned specifically that if you use AI
to write your papers, you're giving away your voice.
And for some of you,
that may make you sound more
like a white male than you want.
And so it's very important for students to be aware
of kind of not only the ramifications
of academic integrity and all that,
but also that we want their original work.
We want their voices to be heard
because that's how we make a better society, et cetera.
So, the conversations that Lynn kind of provoked
with this prompt here,
we're gonna have different ones with different stakeholders.
The administrators are going to be like,
how do we stay ahead of this?
For the students, it's like,
we know you're already doing it.
And then sometimes you might be doing it
even if the instructor asks you not to.
And in some cases it might be questionable.
So, and again, in my syllabus, I say,
before you ask AI to write your paper,
ask me the teacher for an extension and see how that works.
And so when we start engaging people on our campuses
and our districts and throughout the consortial regions
in conversations around AI,
let's be active listeners,
let's hear what the challenges people are that they perceive
or are actually feeling,
and then figure out ways that we can work together
to keep moving forward.
- Thank you, Kevin. Did you have more to add?
- I'd like to respond to a couple things
that Kevin brought up and
the other acronym that's the big acronym in the AI space
and kind of AI policy and guidelines
is the HUMANS Principles.
And we do have a T-shirt
with the HUMANS Principles on it now.
So, I should, yeah, kind of get the website out to y'all
because I was wearing it at the AI Fellows Retreat
on Monday.
And it's great, it's another acronym,
and the U in HUMAN stands for kind of universal access
and universal design.
And that gets to the point that we should not be amplifying
the digital divide through the use of AI.
And then that directly tracks to the announcement
that Google made this morning about the MOU signing
and the availability of premium level tools
for all of our students in the system,
which is something the Chancellor very much wants.
Now of course, that has to get turned on
district by district and college by college,
which means having the conversation locally about,
you know, developing AI literacy at your campus.
So, are you ready to turn on those functions?
Is this something that there is agreement on?
And kind of what are the step-by-step processes
to get to a place where that makes sense to do locally,
under local control?
But that option is now available,
which is incredibly exciting.
And so we'll see, you know, how that starts to play out
at different campuses around the state.
So, just wanted to kind of add that on.
- Yeah, thank you,
because that leads right into the next query, which is,
you know, it's very clear that we're committed
to developing AI literacy, at least all of us up here.
You know, like AI literacy is important,
especially AI literacy around using it effectively,
appropriately, ethically, and transparently.
And that goes for faculty and for students.
And the question then becomes, that's the what,
the question then becomes, how?
How do we do that?
So, do you guys know?
- I have only personal approaches to offer here.
So, I like the acronym focus here.
So I'll share one more that I came up with from my class
and how I approach AI in that room.
The first thing was obviously having
an AI policy on the syllabus
so the students understood that in my class
they would be exposed to it.
They would be using ChatGPT, Midjourney, a few other tools
that we were using for graphics, artwork, et cetera.
And I give them prompts to use. So, that's just upfront.
Then I created this thing that I was like,
acronyms, right?
TRUST, right? We love this word.
And so I said, well, you just mentioned transparency.
So, that's actually what the first T stands for.
So it's use AI with transparency.
No hiding it. On my end either, by the way.
Responsibility, are you using it responsibly?
What does that even mean?
A conversation that we've been having here at this summit.
It's absolutely clear that there is levels of usage,
but we determine to be responsible or irresponsible.
So, whatever you determine in your classroom
as part of your academic freedom,
you can make that much AI be part of the class.
Use it responsibly based on these guidelines.
We also have statewide and national guidelines.
I mean, AI is really a global conversation,
so we should abide by the statewide guidelines, certainly,
but it is a global conversation.
So seeing that others,
other countries, other states,
other parts of the world are looking at this technology too.
You get a bigger impression on,
well, what is this gonna look like in a global sense?
So, use it transparently, use it responsibly,
use it with understanding.
That implies misusage.
That implies you play a little bit
to make some mistakes, right?
One of my favorite teachers is Ms. Frizzle.
Take chances, make mistakes, get messy.
Absolutely.
So, use it with understanding of when you should
and when you shouldn't.
That's part of AI literacy too.
Digital literacy is what it was called earlier.
I agree with that.
Use it with strategy.
Again, that requires some higher order thinking here.
I hear a lot of talk of AI diminishing critical thinking.
I'm like, I don't think that that has to be the case.
There are strategies and approaches we could use
to mitigate that, to have them use AI more strategically.
And then the final one is tenacity.
And I like this word because it's this grit focused word.
Be tenacious, don't give up, don't quit.
Try again.
One of my first policies in my syllabus
is that weak prompts will make for weak outputs.
So, we've all heard here that prompting is good to learn.
It's part of this new literacy
that's now being required by jobs, et cetera.
So, I would say trust your students, lead with trust,
but it's not trust that comes just with nothing there.
It's like, I gave you the tools, I gave you guidelines,
I gave you frameworks, I gave you transparency and trust.
And I lead with that, because I hear too many conversations
here about over-policing students and unethical usage
is always the default conversation.
I'm like, we can have a far more critical,
higher order thinking conversation too.
- Thank you. I totally agree with that.
The culture of trying to catch them
for doing something wrong
is just not the best, healthiest classroom feel, you know?
Craig, did you have something to add to this?
- Yeah, there are a lot of false positives
and false negatives with that approach,
and of trying to catch students out
and kind of just block AI entirely.
I mean, that sort of genie is out of the bottle, right?
And depending which survey you look at,
you'll see different levels of AI usage,
but we all know it's quite prevalent among students.
And so Rodrigo, let me ask you,
is the TRUST acronym,
are you including that in your syllabus, or is that,
yeah, so that would be one approach I think
that would be wonderful
if we could just kind of universally understand
that students need to know about your position
in your classroom on the use of AI.
And the Academic Senate for California Community Colleges
put out a terrific paper called Academic Integrity
in the Era of Artificial Intelligence.
And in that document, they advocate for including
like sort of a meter or a dial, right,
from wide open, you know, go for it,
use AI for anything,
to it's okay within certain parameters,
and we're gonna discuss what those parameters are,
to, you know, this is a closed,
there's no AI permitted in this class.
And that's fine, right? Because that's academic freedom.
And I think, you know, most,
when we have done surveys of faculty
across the California Community College system,
there may be some response bias
in who's responding to those surveys,
but it seems like the majority of folks
are sort of in the open to, you know,
somewhat moderated use of AI.
And students need to know that
because they can get shut down.
When we listen to students' experiences, like for instance,
around the Nectar AI pilot, some students are very reluctant
to engage with an AI tool that instructor's
are encouraging them to use
because they've been told that using AI is cheating.
And we're just not being clear enough with our students.
So, again, I think that comes right back
to what is our policy and, you know,
getting to a point where we can agree institutionally
what our position is and accepting
the different kind of positionalities
that need to happen vis-a-vis AI use.
But just, again, transparency I think
is a good word for that.
Being very transparent about what that use policy is,
class by class, syllabus by syllabus,
but including it in every syllabus
would be a great kind of step towards achieving AI literacy.
- And since my colleagues on the panel have focused heavily
on thinking of the teaching and learning roles with policy,
I'll step aside for a second
and talk to any administrators in the room,
any technology experts.
So, the policies that we have to consider
in addition to academic integrity
and things like that are data governance.
This morning we heard Chancellor Christian talk about,
hey, what if we could enable staff to use AI
to streamline workflows regardless of what those are?
And there might be ways to investigate that.
But if we just let the horses run wild out of the corral,
does that mean that someone might take data sets
that have personally identifiable information
and throw it into something that's gonna train
one of the language learning models?
So we need to be thinking about
the different aspects of AI use across the institution
and consider, like, how does this impact student services?
Right now we're about to launch a tool
in the far north region with three rural colleges
to use a multi-channel AI-based platform called Cali
to support students as they apply for the college,
as they register for classes, as they fill out the FAFSA,
as they seek basic needs.
And the thing I love about it is
they might have filled out a lot of the forms,
but then it'll prompt them with a text message saying,
"Hey, you haven't registered for classes yet.
Do you wanna do that now? Let me tell you how."
And so to me those are ways to approach
when you say how do we approach AI adoption on a campus.
I think it means first being inclusive.
Which people need to be at the table for conversations
about what does it mean that we're gonna start using AI
in an intentional manner, not a haphazard ad hoc way.
But we're gonna have maybe an overarching vision.
This college is gonna be in line with the Chancellor
and we're going to make sure that our students
are ready for an AI-enabled workforce,
but we're gonna do so in a way that's responsible
so that the students are learning the difference
between using it to do the work
and using it to streamline work, right?
And so when we think about the different roles
at our colleges that might interact with AI,
the policy development, and again,
I'll use the version policy versus guidelines
because sometimes policy means, is this a board policy?
Is this an administrative procedure?
Or is this something that we are telling people,
we want you to adhere to this guideline
because it's a best practice or effective practice,
however you want to characterize it.
And again, thinking about data governance,
thinking about change management,
because this wave of AI, right now we're in the mid stages
of gen AI and the early stages of agentic AI.
Soon, it'll be robotic AI,
or then whatever term they'll come up with, right?
So we want to start thinking about,
if we're developing policies,
how do we make something that fits,
it's kind of future-proofed, right?
So, we don't have to redo this every year.
We'll wanna revisit our policies
and see is there a downstream effect?
If we put this in place, do we have to change other things
that we've got in place in our college pantheon
of words on pages.
So, it's really just thinking about a holistic view.
But I would say, if anyone's read Charles Duhigg,
the ways we can make our team better and more successful,
it means diversity, making sure we have
a lot of different voices in the room.
And that could be age, gender, ethnicity,
but also experiences in the world.
I strongly advocate having students in those
and I know they're hard to capture.
So, maybe offer a pizza here and there.
And then thinking about, again, an intentional approach.
And think big, start small
is probably my last piece of advice
because there's a lot to do and not much time
and we're all busy people.
So, hey, we're gonna try to get this done this semester
and we feel we can do that.
- Thank you. Did you have more to add?
- I do, Kevin always seems to spark
some additional thoughts for me.
- He's inspiring. - As well as you Rodrigo.
The trust thing is really sticking with me.
The U now, the understanding.
And understanding really, you know,
kind of how to move policy forward for this system,
which we may have some policy experts in the room
and others that are policy newbies,
but it kind of has to start either
with the inherent authority of the system
or maybe a legislative need
or regulation that's been instituted into policy.
So, if we were to look at AI, you know,
putting AI literacy into policy,
it might start with the inherent authority
of the Chancellor's Office to set the standards
and the philosophy of our associate's degree.
And in there, you know, when you look into
those sections of Title V that address those areas,
you'll see that there's a philosophy statement
about what our students should know generally.
There's some very specific guidance around GE,
but also some general guidance around,
you know, numeracy and literacy.
And these are, when I look at those,
it reminds me of our institutional learning outcomes
that most campuses have developed
and have up on their website.
So, that's a place, we might have information literacy,
or media literacy there,
and kind of information, media, and AI/AI literacy.
So, that might be a place where this type of literacy
really naturally slots in.
So, that could be part of the how.
And I say that knowing that
at the next consultation council,
this is coming forward for sort of the general discussion
of the different constituencies represented
at the consultation council and to,
you know, discuss how do we kind of create that hook
that lets colleges and districts know
that AI literacy is part of the game, right?
Is part of what students should be achieving
when they exit our institutions as alum
and enter the workforce.
And you know, I think probably people in this room
are very well aware that AI skills
are incredibly in demand in the workforce right now.
And they're an important differentiator
as to whether a student gets hired or not,
or how much they get paid.
There is a 400% increase in the incidence
of AI skills being listed in job postings last year,
and in one year.
And positions that include AI skills in the job description
get paid on average $18,000 more
than those that don't, right?
So, that matters a lot.
It matters deeply to our students and our alum and to us.
Moreover, there was a survey that LinkedIn did
of 30,000 plus employers and decision makers
who 67% of them said they wouldn't even consider hiring
someone that didn't have AI skills.
So, you know, that is a call to action for us.
So, when you look at that, we realize,
now this is a fundamental,
this kind needs to be wrapped in at that level
and we need to have the dialogue
about how that happens, right?
We're not trying to, you know, push it
without the necessary dialogue,
but I think we need to start having that conversation.
And it begins with that, you know,
the conversation we're having here.
I look forward to hearing, you know,
the questions and thoughts of folks in this room as well.
So, I'm gonna be quiet so there's some room
for Q&A at the end of this.
- Well, I just, before we do that,
because all of you have alluded to the idea that we are,
that we have goals, right?
As a system, we have goals
and we're building policies that move us toward those goals.
And we don't wanna have to rewrite those policies
every six months and stuff.
So, what does responsible AI use look like
in both the classroom and the workplace?
What are we aiming for here?
- I think fundamental understanding.
One example that I can kind of point back to,
and it's an early story, so bear with me here.
We're going back to 2022 and ChatGPT has just emerged.
And you know, I'm an English professor,
so I'm just kind of typing away, what is this doing?
And the first thing that I did
was put in my prompt for my essay.
I was like, whoa.
So then I said, I'm taking this into class tomorrow,
and I put it in front of my students.
I gave them a 20, 30 minute timeframe.
I said please write a response to this right here.
Said, great, nothing out of the ordinary.
We're writing in class. Great.
And then I said, okay, now look.
And I showed them.
And they were like, what is this professor?
Why are you showing us this?
And that became the starting point for what was honestly,
like, the best, critical conversations
that I've had in my class about authorship, writing,
what is writing, what is thinking, all of it.
They were like, who's composing this then?
And I had a student who,
talk about making arguments, right,
was very willing to argue that because she wrote
the sentence that led to the output of the essay
that she was person who wrote the essay.
I was like, this is a moment for this literacy that we need.
Like, no, you did not write the essay,
but you did prompt it and you were happy with the output.
Now, let's consider the output.
And really, I teach English,
but I like to say rather I teach rhetoric.
And I think rhetoric is having a revival in this moment
because any new technology that has ever emerged,
and that includes writing as a technology,
we have to think about it
through those rhetorical questions.
And that saves you from the conversation of,
what happens when this new technology emerges?
Because new technologies always emerge.
So, we go at those new technologies
with the same fundamental, rhetorical, critical questions,
frame it for our students in that way.
And trust me, they will have productive,
critical conversations.
And yes, some will misuse the technology. Absolutely.
But we've heard great strategies here at the summit
for how to mitigate that.
- I love that phrase, the revival of rhetoric.
Goosebumps there.
Did you wanna add anything, either Kevin or Craig?
It's up to you.
- I'll pass.
- Could you repeat the question?
I got caught up in what Rodrigo was saying?
- Really? - Yeah.
- Oh, okay.
We're aiming for responsible AI use.
We're writing policies to get us there.
What is it? What does it look like?
Where are we going with this?
- Well, I think, you know,
a policy needs to be written in a way
that's appropriate to the level,
and that means it's general enough
that it gives guidance, but it's not,
we had in our crazy, wonderful system,
we have local control, right?
So, it's not gonna be at a state level.
It can be more directive, I suppose.
But a lot of our policy is more about guidelines, right?
It's about kind of establishing that conversation, saying,
now, go forth locally, have the conversation,
decide for yourself, you know,
do you want to adopt the HUMANS Principles
that have been, you know,
kind of developed and promulgated by the AI Council?
They're there for the taking.
Do you need to develop your own version
of that locally so it makes sense?
You've got some refinements and tweaks to make.
But you need something, right?
Basically, it's saying you need something.
So, it's a call to action.
And then there's guidance and helpful,
hopefully, helpful guidance,
to make it happen in a timely fashion.
Because time is of the essence here in that,
you know, students are,
I assume many of us have read the articles
about students entering the job market
and kind of the entry level rungs of that career ladder
getting cut off in a lot of different professions.
And so they need all the help they can get landing
that first job and getting themselves going
in their career trajectory.
So, there is a sense of urgency, but there's also agency,
and there's a need to kind of step up
and define that for yourselves
in the context of your local community.
- Great, thank you.
So, last question before we open it
for Q&A from the audience.
And that's a cue for you to start thinking
what you're gonna ask.
What's off limits?
What kind of things are out of bounds
when it comes to AI use?
What kind of things are we saying,
no, that's not a
ethical, appropriate, effective approach to using it?
- I'll jump in there.
And one of the things that we looked at
as we were kind of reviewing the literature
on AI literacy, you know,
the AI Council didn't invent the term AI literacy.
There's a lot of research that had been done
over the years into what that comprises,
you know, from four elements to twenty-four elements.
And, you know, we sort of settled on the six
that are embodied in the HUMANS Principles
as a good kind of distillation of the essence
of the most important elements of AI literacy.
One of the things we looked at that was informative,
we had a pretty rich discussion,
was the EU AI Act.
And the EU AI Act, there was a similar legislation
that came forward in California
and ultimately the governor didn't sign it
because what was similar is it was
a risk-based approach to AI, right?
And, oh no, well, he didn't sign our version
because it wasn't risk-based.
The EU AI Act has a risk-based.
So, it was just sort of, like,
lumped all AI together, the California version.
But if you look at the EU AI Act,
there's this pyramid kind of structure to it.
And at the top is just unacceptable uses of AI.
There's certain stuff you should not,
it is not permissible.
And, you know, no policy should allow, for instance,
using AI to subliminally manipulate people.
That's not okay, right?
Like, we don't support that. That's off limits.
Other uses is kind of scooping up public video,
audio feeds and biometrically processing that
without people's awareness, right?
So, those are kind of the two, like,
signature kind of unacceptable uses.
Right under that there's a high-risk zone
and that's using AI for critical infrastructure.
And high-risk doesn't mean you can't use it,
but it means there needs to be a human in the loop
to break that cycle,
and that there's a rigorous sort of safety protocol in place
to make sure that humans can kind of intercede.
And guess what else is in there?
Educational assessment.
And hiring and employment.
So, educational decisions and hiring decisions.
So, that means we shouldn't just be turning the keys over
to whatever AI has been integrated into Canvas
and say, grade my students and, you know,
I just set that class on autopilot
and I'll check in at the end
when I have to submit the grades, right?
That is not an ethical and appropriate,
so, but it's fine to,
you know, there's a lot of different ways to use,
I'm not saying don't do it, right?
There's a lot of different ways to do that
that would be ethical, transparent.
And, you know, for instance,
the ability to have frequent low-stakes assessment,
the AI can empower that in a very helpful
and useful way that can promote student learning.
But it needs to be done mindfully, right?
In an intentional pedagogical framework
that the instructor is laying out, right?
And that's, I think, we're all in agreement with that.
We're not trying to replace our, you know,
wonderful, magical educational experience
that students have with human instructors with AI.
But there are certainly applications of AI
to that experience that are very helpful
and can allow for more time for deeper conversations
and human interaction that support engagement and learning.
So, I think that would be, you know,
kind of one example that's been helpful
for me to think about what's off limits
and what, you know, needs strong guidelines, and so on.
- I had a couple thoughts.
So, Craig brought up a very specific set of use cases
of things that have been identified,
but we're always gonna be behind the curve, right?
Somebody's gonna think of something
we haven't thought of yet.
And we have policies in place about student behavior,
about faculty and staff behavior.
We have handbooks and all these things.
So, really it boils down to, like,
the culture of the institution.
Are you doing something that you shouldn't be knowingly?
And if you're doing something unwittingly,
then how do we educate you back in the literacy
and fluency conversation.
To your point about things like,
hey, I'd love to use AI to give students feedback,
maybe, you know, it's what I've suggested
to some of the learning management system developers,
rather than making it a teacher-facing tool,
make it a student-facing tool.
In my class, I have always had peer review.
It's a writing intensive class
and I love the revival of rhetoric
because I have to do that, too.
But I also now have students compare AI feedback
to this human student feedback.
And what are the benefits that they get from both?
What is each one missing?
So, they're actually reflecting on what feedback is
and how to generate more valuable feedback for their peers.
So, there are ways that we as educators
can be thinking about the implications of AI.
And again, it's being intentional about it rather than,
hey, there's this tool,
I'm gonna press a button and trust the results.
What is the O, like, observe and verify,
or something like that?
So, I'm gonna get these acronyms if it kills me.
- There's a lot to it.
- And in the spirit of, like,
modify them for your own college culture,
I suggest nobody turn HUMANS into ROBOTS.
Because that's also six letters and probably not-
(audience and panel laughing)
But you get my point, right?
So, the same way we can future-proof policies,
we can also future-proof our approaches
by thinking kind of at a deeper level.
How are we asking students
to behave in our campus community?
How do we take less of a risk-based approach
and more of an asset-based approach and say,
hey, you're bringing your strengths.
We want you to capitalize on those
and use them in ways that are appropriate.
And we're gonna have open conversations about it.
So, to your point about grading again,
I had a conversation with my students in an online class,
what do you all think about AI
in the teaching and learning context?
And the highest liked responses were,
"I don't like it when other students use AI
to write their papers
because I took the time to write mine."
And, "I don't like it when teachers use AI
to grade my papers because I'm paying tuition
and I want to get the value of the expert in the room
who I chose as my instructor."
And so the students, you know,
I know there's a lot of concern about what could go wrong,
but the students are aware of those things as well
and are thinking intelligently about it.
And so if we just have candid conversations with them
about what's appropriate,
I think we can not worry so much about,
let's make a list of things that are not approved
and more, let's all work together to get this done.
- Building a culture of trust.
- Yeah, TRUST is the acronym.
- Yes, happy to follow up those great responses
with a single sort of idea that I've come to.
It's that the only thing that is not allowed in my class
as far as AI is relegating your thinking
or your agency to the machine.
That's it.
So, let me actually go through my AI policy
so you understand exactly why, though,
it's sort of built into the policy itself
and you can see how each one of these three bullet points
addresses that very fact.
So number one, if you provide,
well, first AI is one of the emerging Web3 tools
that promises to shake up both academia
and the professional landscape.
Regardless of how you feel about it,
learning to use it well is an emerging and valuable skill.
Let's start there. Right?
That being said, you can expect to use AI in my classes,
ChatGPT, Midjourney, at a minimum.
Now, please be aware,
one, if you provide minimum prompts,
you will get low-quality results.
You'll need to refine your prompts
in order to achieve better outcomes.
This will take work.
So, again, weak outputs, you gotta work at them, right?
We've heard a lot of that actually today
about how prompting and refining is a good thing to teach.
Number two, don't trust anything.
AI, in this case ChatGPT, says,
assume facts it gives you a wrong,
unless you know the answer
or can check it with another source.
You will be responsible for any errors
or omissions provided by the tool.
It works best for topics you understand.
And three, any use of AI tools must be acknowledged,
going back to the transparency.
Please be sure to include a paragraph
at the end of any assignment that uses AI
explaining what you used it for
and the specific prompts you used to get your results.
Failure to do so is in violation
of academic honesty policies.
So, the idea there was,
I heard that now we have the MLA and APA
giving us citation methodologies, which is great.
At the time there wasn't any, so it was like,
how about you just cite your inputs or your outputs
as part of your work cited
because now you know you can export those.
So, give me the input and the output that you used,
add that as an addendum to your work,
and we're good to go.
There is inherent trust there.
So, do not relegate your thinking to the machine
is all I would say, agentic or not.
- I love that policy. Do you mind if we steal it?
- It's in the list of the,
who put this together?
- Lance Eaton. - Lance Eaton's list.
It's number 76 if you wanna find mine.
- Yeah, I don't know if if you all know about it,
but Lance Eaton has compiled policies
from faculty all over the,
is it just the country or the world?
- Everywhere. It's everywhere.
- And how many are in there now?
- There's at least 150 or something.
130.
- There's some great examples in there
from all different disciplines.
And so if you're looking for inspiration
for your own policy.
That that was a great policy.
Okay, so, what do you guys think is best,
if we make closing statements and then take questions,
or take questions and then make closing statements?
- Questions. - Questions first?
Okay. There's some hands up.
Okay, I'm gonna get up here and steal somebody's mic.
Thank you, Kevin. Is it on?
Okay, where is a hand?
- [Kathy] Man, I have so much to say after all that,
but I will limit what I have to say.
I'm with you. I'm an English professor.
And I also started adapting it in my courses
pretty quickly after 2022.
But I'm also helping to craft our AI policies on our campus.
And I use PlayLab in my classes.
And recently, in my last few semesters,
I spend time on AI literacy,
even though it's an English course,
and about prompting.
And they took, I asked them after,
I assessed whatever they thought of that AI literacy bit
that I gave them and they took away,
which I thought was kind of impressive,
that their critical thinking skills,
who they are, is the most important skill
they don't wanna lose to ChatGPT, or whomever or whatever.
So, that's good. So I'm a proponent.
And I'm trying to work with my faculty
and train my students and et cetera.
But the one thing that I am concerned about is,
earlier you mentioned about the models sounding
like a white male, right?
And I do spend some time in my AI literacy portion
about, not to trust the machine,
to verify, check, et cetera.
And I show a little clip about
how really it can cross lines
in terms of not representing everybody,
especially certain groups that are underrepresented.
So my concern is, as we move forward,
and we're making these deals with the vendors,
and it's great, we have all these tools and everything,
I feel like we're piling on top of everything
all these wonderful tools, yes,
but on the baseline foundational model.
And are we ever gonna go backwards
and go back to the training part of it
and try to make that more diverse?
I don't know the answer, I'm just curious.
- I would say that one of the ways
that you can deal with some of the bias,
because of course we know AI, how it works, right?
It works off of the data sets that you feed it,
is by being very intentional with your prompting.
So, one example that I can use from the visual space mainly
is I have a lot of caricatures of myself
that I make for my professional development.
So, if you see one of my professional development,
you'll see a little avatar of me wearing a jacket.
Anyway, to make that,
I didn't want to insert a picture of myself,
upload a picture of myself.
It was early on in the conversation where I was like,
I don't know if I want to upload personal things,
personal names, personal anything.
So, I said, give me a picture
of a professor teaching a class.
Well, that's too general.
Then I said, give me a picture of a professor
with a beard, glasses, brown skin.
Nailed it.
If you think of it that way, then again,
you can control the outputs
because you're aware of how it works.
It generalizes knowledge in a very specific way,
so you can ask for more specific outputs
is how I sort of turn to that.
You can't avoid going back to train the initial model
to have this data or whatever,
but you can work with smaller dataset models,
like NotebookLM.
You can create your own open source ones
that can have limited knowledge.
You can do things sort of to circumvent that.
But it's a very big issue.
And I think really having that exact conversation
with them is the best thing.
- And if I can tack onto that,
so, I think that it becomes part of
the AI literacy conversation and fluency
when we're supporting students,
even if we could, and it's a great idea,
to have the California Community Colleges create
their own LLM, other institutions are doing it,
A, I'm pretty sure, and Craig will check me if I'm wrong,
that the Google agreement
is in enterprise-level data protections
and it's not gonna be used to train any models.
But it does mean that we're using
the one that they have now,
and so we need to train students to use the models
not only that they're gonna use
when they're at our institutions,
but that they're gonna use when they're out in the workforce
because they're going to encounter AI
that's biased in some way, shape, or form.
And we want them to be able to know what to do with that.
And it gets back to the verify,
but also in the humans, it's the algorithmic bias.
How are we telling our students to consider that
when they look at the results, and make adjustments for it
so that they're producing something
that they believe represents them and their communities
and everybody else that they believe
is part of their network.
- Yeah, and sorry, what college are you?
- Napa Valley College. - Napa Valley College. Okay.
And what's your name? - Kathy.
- Kathy. Thanks.
And so, Kathy, I think Rodrigo said,
you mentioned NotebookLM,
and one of the things you could do
is to basically call it a RAG plus LLM,
which is retrieval augmented generation,
means you upload your own sources to it
and then you can focus the attention of the LLM
on those sources first.
So, there's different,
like Notebook LLM lets you do that.
Nectar AI lets you do that.
You can create custom GPTs in ChatGPT that let you do that.
And then that way you can kind of bring,
you can surface that kind of perspective
and the voices that you want to make sure
are represented in the output.
And so that's a nice kind of, you know,
tool that you have available to make sure that
you're kind of surfacing the perspectives
that need to be included in the conversation with the AI.
- [Lynn] Okay. We have another question here.
- [Participant] Thank you. Thank you for this panel.
I wanted to ask about resistance
to conceptualizing agency in artificial intelligence.
In other words, not just skepticism,
but outright refusal to consider this new technology,
relatively new technology, as part of their work.
To frame it, I taught for a number of years
at a mountain village in Southern Africa
where we didn't have electricity
or running water or mimeograph machines.
Our technology consists of chalk.
And then to frame it one more further,
and I'd like your perspectives on this resistance,
in the Socratic dialogue, writing will produce
the appearance of wisdom, not true wisdom,
for they will seem to know many things when they are,
for the most part, ignorant, since they are not wise,
but only appear wise.
So, even writing and printing presses and calculators,
remember Texas Instruments was
the death of mathematics, right?
So, tell me about this outright resistance
a layer beyond skepticism?
- So, I think with any technology innovation,
there's an entire adoption curve,
if you're familiar with it, by Rogers,
where you have early adopters,
a early majority, a late majority,
and then the tail end,
which people use sometimes derogatory terms,
resisters might be one.
When I first started in faculty development,
I had an instructor who had a printed out, typewritten sheet
that students would hand write their attendance.
And we were talking to him
about different strategies he could use.
It would be easier, less work.
And he's like, "I will never get a computer."
This is, you know, back when people
were getting desktops and such.
And two years after he retired,
I saw him at the bookstore using his alumni pass
to get a computer.
And I said, "What convinced you to finally make the change?"
And he goes, "My grandson wanted to email me."
So, it's finding out what's meaningful
for the people who are resisting
and what is causing the resistance.
Like, we said earlier today,
I really feel like I should have started
with a psychology degree in this field
because we need to understand the underlying motivations,
or lack of motivation,
for people to at least have conversations.
We're not asking everybody to do this.
We're making it opt-in, right?
At the institution level and at the human level.
And so those resisters are going to exist.
We want their voices in the conversation
if they're willing to participate,
but at some point, as we've already said,
it's here and we need to keep moving forward.
So, we hope you'll join us as kind of an invitation.
- [Lynn] Pretty much says it, right?
- I would say, I have a very easy sort of answer to this,
because I teach writing and rhetoric to my students.
So, when they are reluctant,
I'm like, okay, cool.
Reluct away.
Because all that means is we're gonna focus on syntax
and grammar and sentences and complex structures
and meaning-making,
and that inherently will make you a good prompter.
That's a default, though. Don't worry about it, right?
That's not what we're focusing on.
We're gonna focus on just composition and communication.
So, they are reluctant in my class sometimes,
and despite my policy, I say,
you don't want to use it, that's okay.
It's fine.
But you should know that others will,
and that there is jobs that are now demanding it,
and that you are now in this conversation,
this thing that's here whether you want it to or not,
and you'd better prepare yourself.
Because, you know, we've all heard that quote, I'm sure,
that AI will not replace you, but someone using AI will.
And I see that happening more and more, just people,
Fabi earlier was talking about how capitalism
just keeps putting more work in front of you, right?
But definitely we can do more work with the help of AI,
but that shouldn't be the goal.
- [Steve] Thank you so much for this panel.
Steve Lisowski, professor of nursing
at Hartnell Community College.
I just wanted to share two real quick experiences
that I had a little bit along the lines
of what you were talking about
with administrators and that kind of thing.
A different perspective that came to me was,
I'm one of the few people at my college who's using AI,
and what was interesting was the perspective of the teacher.
In other words, how it changed my perspective
about how I taught,
kind of to what you were saying, Rodrigo,
about prompts, but not only prompts to the AI,
but in prompting the AI, how that helped me
actually engage with the students better
in terms of discussion and that kind of thing,
that looking for the quote unquote "right answer."
And then the other thing that you all spoke of
was this kind of interesting pervasiveness of,
I've gone to a couple AI conferences now
that often focus on the catching the student type thing,
the cheating, you know, paradigm.
And I just, I think one of you said it,
Rodrigo, I think it was you,
you said that, like, the students are almost more aware
of the situation than we can be.
And I had a student who used Grammarly.
And so she had this amazing paper
and her conversational tactics were significantly different.
So, I just mentioned it to her in-person,
and she said, "Oh, you know, well I use Grammarly."
And I said, "Oh, okay, well, you know,
as of right now, we have a policy that we can't use AI."
So, I said, "Okay, well did you use AI?"
"No, I used Grammarly."
And I said, "Well, I think Grammarly now uses AI,"
you know, kind of thing.
She was absolutely terrified.
Like, the concept,
it wasn't that she was trying to cheat,
she was literally falling apart
that she was gonna get dropped from the program.
And I was like, no, no, no,
that's not what we're talking about.
But my point is to what a lot of you have said,
we bring, like anything,
a bias to this new technology.
And I think it's not only important for us
as we develop these policies,
we need to be aware of our own biases
that we're bringing to the table.
- Absolutely.
And just to kind of follow up your point there,
I'm doing far more work now that AI's here
than before it was here.
So, the whole idea of how it frees up your time
and all that, I don't think so.
- So true. So true.
So, I think I've been showing a bias
for that side of the room.
So, here, we've got some questions over here.
- [Participant] I just have a question and a comment.
I'll start with my comment first,
I took a AI class for business
and it really opened my eyes to look at it
from a very different perspective.
And I know we have focused a lot on English,
but one of the things that this course did
is that it gave us videos of industry leaders
and what they expected from their employees.
And very often, they were wanting the employees
to use AI to write reports.
And so that was something that was very interesting,
because I'm like, well, we're in higher ed,
and we're telling students not to do that,
but here we have industry that's saying
this is what they're gonna need to do the report.
And even in the medical field,
it was just amazing to see how AI is saving lives.
And I kind of reflected on being stuck.
You know, we're stuck in these spots,
and a lot of our conversation is focused on
what do we have to do to prevent
all of these other things from happening?
So, I just wanna challenge us to really focus on,
including myself, to really focus on how we can embrace it
and really empower our students to use it.
Because the fear factor is there for our students.
Even in our syllabus, if we say you can use it,
but here's all these, you know,
specifications as to, or limitations.
And so I also teach sometimes
and I was looking at my own syllabus,
and I looked back and I was, like,
all I could see is like, no, no, no, no, no,
versus, in order to maximize your learning,
this is what you have to do.
So, just really kind of being reflective on that.
And so I appreciate all of the points
that everyone has brought up
because it's just sparked more ambition
to try to continue to do that work.
And my second part has to do with
kind of bigger pieces, institutional policies.
There was conversation earlier on about data governance.
Are there best practices?
Are there models out there for institutions?
Because we are just piecemealing different pieces.
And it would be great for us to have some of that guidance
so that we can help guide teachers,
but also our overall administrative structures
in how employees can use them.
Because our employees are already using them all the time.
And whether they're purchasing them with the CAL-Card
or whether they have the free version,
you know, they're out there.
And so, and then the last piece that I just wanna emphasize,
and I don't know if anyone
from the Chancellor's Office is here,
is just getting consistency
in funding for these software products
because there's so much out there,
and it's almost like the iPhone and the Android, you know?
But now we have all these other options
and it can be very overwhelming,
especially when administration
has to make difficult decisions
on what type of funding or what type of tool and technology.
The dollars matter in different spaces.
So, I just wanted to emphasize that,
but any samples or examples on best practices
for governance would be appreciated.
- So, I can start that conversation.
The same way that you demonstrated
a list of syllabus policies,
a gentleman named Joe Sabado from UC Santa Barbara
has put together a comprehensive analysis
of around 200 policies at the campus level
at colleges and universities.
And I think there's a writeup.
So, I'll see if I can find that.
But that would be a place to start.
And there are other repositories
of institution-level policies.
And so we'll, I don't know if there's gonna be show notes
for this panel or something in the schedule,
but we can work with the organizers of this conference
to make sure that there's a place
to get things that were mentioned.
Oh, go ahead.
- I'm, I'm looking at the time
and I'm seeing people bail on us and I don't blame them.
So, and I know that there were more hands up,
and there were more questions, so I don't know
if you are willing to hang out for a little bit
and let people come up and ask you questions,
is that okay for each of you?
Okay, so if you still have questions for the panelists,
we're willing to hang out a bit.
But in the meantime, do you wanna make, like,
a 30-second closing statement and pass it on?
- So my closing statement is I'm in a session in 15 minutes,
so I'm gonna ask you to email me your questions.
kkelly@cccdigitalcenter.org
Or just come find me. I'm the guy wearing this jacket.
And we'll have a chat.
But it's been a privilege to have this conversation
in front of you.
I know it would be nice if we can have more of it with you.
But this is a topic that is,
like AI itself, not gonna go away.
We need to be thinking about, across an institution,
what does adoption mean
and how can we be out in front of it?
- Thank you.
- Closing statement, 30 seconds.
We are launching a new AI microsite,
which is gonna collect our AI resources and be a new,
kind of have some new functionality,
including promoting AI professional development.
So having amazing new tools like NotebookLM,
and, you know, the pro version of Gemini is great,
but you do need to understand things like data governance
and, you know, prompting ethically and responsibly.
And so that will be a place where we're gonna surface
both the amazing work,
because there's such a diversity of cool work happening
on AI around the state regionally,
so, connecting that regional effort
to the state-level effort
and leveraging our newly launched AI Fellows program
to help us sort of coordinate that work regionally
and make that visible.
So, keep an eye out for the launch of that new site.
Should be launching later this month
around the same time that that first AI webinar
is happening on Tuesday, September 30th.
So, also look for the flyer invite,
and please if you're available, join that.
It's a good opportunity.
There's a lot of Q&A and really smart people
that are involved in AI that you can interact with there,
online and real-time,
and as well as just follow up via email.
And if you need to contact me,
I am at the Chancellor's Office.
My email is chayward@cccco.edu.
And thank you very much
for spending this time this afternoon with us.
I really enjoyed hearing everyone's questions
and appreciate that opportunity.
- Closing statement, thank you guys for having me.
I loved talking to you about all of these things
that I've done in my classroom.
I know they're a little bit crazy,
sometimes a little bit scary to try new technologies,
but students are ready for these conversations.
So, I would say take this back with you to your regions.
Stand up to be those leaders that we need in those regions.
And then you can come up and sit in the panel here
and I'll sit over there watching, you know,
taking notes when you guys are talking.
So, just literally get involved in the conversation.
You're already here.
So, just take it back, extend from here.
And thank you guys again.
- And thank you for coming.
This is the leading edge thinkers right here.
Look around you. (audience applauding)